Willard Rhodes papers
American Folklife Center, Library of Congress
Guides to the Collections in the Archive of Folk Culture
Willard Rhodes papers 1938-1979
AFC 1980/041
United States. Bureau of Indian Affairs
Rhodes, Willard, 1901-1992
140 items; 2 containers; .6 linear feet.
11 photographs: film negatives, black and white.
39 photographic prints: black and white; various sizes.
1 photographic print: color; 3 x 4 in.
16 field notebooks.
16 folders.
Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Field notebooks, correspondence, publications, and photographs, related to Willard Rhodes' field expeditions to Native American communities between 1938 and 1952 on behalf of the Library of Congress and the Bureau of Indian Affairs. The notebooks contain Rhodes' field notes, transcriptions, translations, and some musical notation, relating to audio recordings of Native American songs. Correspondence (1948-1979) relates primarily to the ten albums of Native American music recorded and edited by Rhodes in the Music of the American Indian series. Tribes recorded by Rhodes include Apache, Bannock, Caddo, Cherokee, Cheyenne, Chinook, Choctaw, Comanche, Creek, Delaware, Hopi, Kiowa, Klallam, Lummi, Navajo, Omaha, Paiute, Pawnee, Potawatomi, Pueblo, Quinault, San Ildefonso, Seminole, Shaker, Shoshone, Sioux, Skagit, Taos, Tewa, Tlingit, Tsaiyak, Ute, Washo, Wichita, and Zuni songs. The collections also includes eight government and mission publications from Sioux communities.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Lange, Juel E.; Rhodes, Willard, 1901-1992; Rhodes, Willard, 1901-1992--Correspondence.
Organizations
United States. Bureau of Indian Affairs
Subjects
Apache Indians--Music.; Bannock Indians--Music.; Caddo Indians--Music.; Cherokee Indians--Music.; Cheyenne Indians--Music.; Chinook Indians--Music.; Choctaw Indians--Music.; Clallam Indians--Music.; Comanche Indians--Music.; Creek Indians--Music.; Dakota Indians--Music.; Delaware Indians--Music.; Field recordings.; Hopi Indians--Music.; Indians of North America--Great Basin.; Indians of North America--Great Lakes Region (North America); Indians of North America--Great Plains.; Indians of North America--Middle Atlantic States.; Indians of North America--Music.; Indians of North America--Southern States.; Indians of North America--Southwest, New.; Kiowa Apache Indians--Music.; Lummi Indians--Music.; Navajo Indians--Music.; Omaha Indians--Music.; Paiute Indians--Music.; Pawnee Indians--Music.; Potawatomi Indians--Music.; Pueblo Indians--Music.; Quinault Indians--Music.; Seminole Indians--Music.; Shoshoni Indians--Music.; Skagit Indians--Music.; Songs, Hopi.; Songs, Lummi.; Songs, Navajo.; Songs, Seminole.; Songs, Tewa.; Songs--Texts.; Taos Indians--Music.; Tewa Indians--Music.; Ute Indians--Music.; Washoe Indians--Music.; Wichita Indians--Music.; Zuni Indians--Music.
Titles
Music of the American Indian.
Form/Genre
Correspondence.; Field notes.; Manuscripts.; Photographs.; Song texts.; Translations.
Arrangement
Collection is arranged in two series: Manuscripts and Visual Materials.
Additional Guides
Inventory is available in the Folklife Reading Room.
Acquisition
Willard Rhodes; 1980.
Related Material
For associated sound recordings see Willard Rhodes field recordings collections, housed at the Archive of Folk Culture, American Folklife Center, Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.:
Willard Rhodes 1940 field recordings collection (AFC 1940/019)
Willard Rhodes 1941 field recordings collection (AFC 1941/039)
Willard Rhodes 1942-1943 field recordings collection (AFC 1942/024)
Willard Rhodes 1943 field recordings collection (AFC 1943/020)
Willard Rhodes 1947 field recordings collection (AFC 1947/012)
Willard Rhodes 1949 field recordings collection (AFC 1949/001)
Willard Rhodes 1950 field recordings collection (AFC 1950/027)
Willard Rhodes 1951 field recordings collection (AFC 1951/001)
Willard Rhodes 1952 field recordings collection (AFC 1952/005)
Some associated original sound recordings reside at UCLA Ethnomusicology Archive.
Access and Restrictions
Collection is open for research. To request materials, please contact the Folklife Reading Room at http://hdl.loc.gov/loc.afc/folklife.contact
Electronic Format
Additional formats include 3396 master digital files, scanned from the originals, 2018.
Biographical Note
While working for the Bureau of Indian Affairs with equipment supplied in part by the Library of Congress, Willard Rhodes, professor of music at Columbia University recorded the music of fifty Native American tribes living primarily in the western United States. He documented, in addition to traditional genres, Christian hymns in native languages, songs with English words, and other music of recent composition. He undertook nine field surveys of Native American music between 1940 and 1952. The recordings included 260 audio discs (1940-1949) and 50 7-inch audio tape reels (1950-1952). The field projects, intended to document new music in Native American communities as well as the traditional music that was being performed, were sponsored by the Bureau of Indian Affairs. The Library of Congress issued ten LP recordings based on the collection through the cooperation of the Bureau of Indian Affairs and the Indian Arts and Crafts Board. Rhodes also edited two albums on Smithsonian Folkways Records. A selection of Native American music, recorded by Rhodes, was released on the Voyager Golden Record (1977).
Scope and Content
Field notebooks, correspondence, publications, and photographs, related to Willard Rhodes' field expeditions to Native American communities between 1938 and 1952 on behalf of the Library of Congress and the Bureau of Indian Affairs. The notebooks contain Rhodes' field notes, transcriptions, translations, and some musical notation, relating to audio recordings of Native American songs. Correspondence (1948-1979) relates primarily to the ten albums of Native American music recorded and edited by Rhodes in the Music of the American Indian series. Tribes recorded by Rhodes include Apache, Bannock, Caddo, Cherokee, Cheyenne, Chinook, Choctaw, Comanche, Creek, Delaware, Hopi, Kiowa, Klallam, Lummi, Navajo, Omaha, Paiute, Pawnee, Potawatomi, Pueblo, Quinault, San Ildefonso, Seminole, Shaker, Shoshone, Sioux, Skagit, Taos, Tewa, Tlingit, Tsaiyak, Ute, Washo, Wichita, and Zuni songs. The collections also includes 8 government and mission publications from Sioux communities.
Photographs of native peoples of Washington State were taken by Juel E. Lange in conjunction Willard Rhodes’ fieldwork. Selected photos were published in the booklet accompanying the original edition of Music of the American Indian: Northwest (Puget Sound) AFS L34. Photographs of Sioux and Pueblo children appear to have been taken by Willard Rhodes. Included in the collection are three 8 x 10 in. black-and-white photographic prints from the Bureau of Indian Affairs of BIA schools.
Container List
- Series 1: Manuscripts
  - Notebook with musical notation, transcriptions, and translations, of Kiowa, Navajo and Sioux songs., June 1938, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1/1)
  - 5 notebooks, music pages, 1939 (Box-folder 1/2)
    - “Indian Music I”- Omaha, South Dakota, July 7-14, 1939, 1 notebook
      Field notes, musical notation, transcriptions, and translations which accompany recordings I-A-1 through XV-B-2.
    - “Indian Music II” Omaha, South Dakota, July 7 and July 17-19, 1939, 1 notebook
      Vocabulary (July 7, 1939); July 17-19, 1939, field notes, transcriptions, translations which accompany recordings VI-B-1 through XVIII-A-3.
    - “Indian Music III” Omaha, South Dakota, July 19-26, 1939, 1 notebook
      Field notes, transcriptions, translations which accompany recordings XVIII-B-2 through XXXI-A-2.
    - “Indian Music IV” Omaha, South Dakota, July 27-28, 1939, 1 notebook
      Field notes, transcriptions, translations which accompany recordings XXXI-B-1 through XXXXIII-A-5.
    - “Indian Music V” Omaha, South Dakota, July 31 - August 5, 1939, 1 notebook
      Field notes, transcriptions, translations which accompany recordings XXXVI-A-1, XXXVII-A-2, XXXXIV-A-1 through L-B-2.
    - Loose music pages, with musical notation and words relating to Omaha songs.
  - "Indian Music XI" Omaha, Navajo, Seminole; South Dakota, New Mexico, California (?), June 6, 1940, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1/3)
    Field notes, transcriptions, translations which accompany recordings I-A-1 through XI. May relate to recordings in AFC 1940/019. One page with notes from 1942/1943.
  - Field notebook: Paiute; Santa Clara, Utah, 1941, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1/4)
    Related recordings: AFC 1941/039
  - Field notebook: Primarily Navajo; Pine Springs, Arizona (1942) and Intermountain Indian School, Brigham City, Utah (1952), August 5-10, 1942; June 14 - July 2, 1952, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1/5)
    Related recordings: AFC 1942/024 and AFC 1952/005
  - 3 notebooks: Alaskan Eskimo, Arikara, Blackfeet, Crow, Flathead, Omaha, Navajo, Nez Perce, Pueblo, Sioux, Wasco, and Winnebago; northern Great Plains and Pacific Northwest, 1947, 3 notebooks (Box-folder 1/6)
    Field notes related to recordings made in the summer of 1947 at Pine Ridge, South Dakota; Chemawa, Simnasho, and Pendleton, Oregon; Toppenish, Washington; Browning and Poplar, Montana; and Elbowoods and Fort Yates, North Dakota. Sponsored by the Bureau of Indian Affairs. Related recordings: AFC 1947/012
  - 3 notebooks: Various tribes and locations, 1950, 3 notebooks (Box-folder 1/7)
    Field notes related to Native American music recorded in the summer of 1950 by Willard Rhodes. Songs are labeled as Puyallup, Canadian/Vancouver Island, Nisqually, Lummi, Snahomish, Skokomish, Snoqualmi, Samyama, Fraser River, Nooksack, Skagit, Samish, Nitinat, Makah, Clayoquot, Quinault, Kwakiutl, Quileute, Chinook, Twana, Chehallis, Bannock, Shoshone, and Arapaho. Included are Native American Shaker songs. Recordings were made at Auburn, Shelton, Marietta, Everson, La Conner, Marblemount, Neah Bay, La Push, Union, Washington; and at Fort Hall, Idaho. Sponsored by the Bureau of Indian Affairs, Education Division. Related recordings: AFC 1950/027.
  - Field notebook: Apache, Cherokee, Comanche, Creek, Hopi, Kiowa, Navajo, Pawnee, Shoshone, and Tlingit, as well as indigenous Ecuadorian and Eskimo music; Arizona, Oklahoma, Oregon, Utah, and Wyoming, 1951, 1 notebook (Box-folder 1/8)
    Field notes related to recordings of Apache, Cherokee, Comanche, Creek, Hopi, Kiowa, Navajo, Pawnee, Shoshone, and Tlingit, as well as indigenous Ecuadorian and Eskimo music. Recorded in Arizona, Oklahoma, Oregon, Utah, and Wyoming by Willard Rhodes, June 1951, for the Bureau of Indian Affairs. Related recordings: AFC 1951/001
  - Trip report, 1952, 6 pages (Box-folder 1/9)
    Discusses fieldwork in Arizona, New Mexico, Oklahoma, and Utah by Willard Rhodes, summer 1952, to collect and record texts of Native American songs to be used in the series of albums of Music of the American Indian by Library of Congress. Related recordings: AFC 1952/005
  - 1948-1954 correspondence (trips and record production) (Box-folder 2/10)
  - 1958-1979 correspondence (Box-folder 2/11)
  - Publications by Rhodes (Box-folder 2/12)
    - “The Use of the Computer in the Classification of Folk Tunes,” Studia Musicologica Tomus VII ( 1965 )
    - “Toward a Definition of Ethnomusicology,” American Anthropologist 58, No. 3 ( June 1956 )
    - “Society of Ethnomusicology,” African Music 1, No. 3 ( 1956 )
    - “A Study of Musical Diffusion Based on the Wandering of the Opening Peyote Song,” Journal of the International Folk Music Council X ( 1958 )
    - “Acculturation in North American Indian Music,” TAX: Acculturation in the Americas, Vol. II, Proceedings of the 29th International Congress of Americanists ( 1952 )
  - 8 Government and mission publications from Sioux communities, including 1936 Constitution and By-laws of the Oglala Sioux Tribe of the Pine Ridge Reservation, South Dakota, 1936 (Box-folder 2/13)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 2/14)
    Lists, text transcriptions, concordance of tracks for Music of the American Indian albums with Rhodes recording numbers, draft of introduction to albums.
- Series 2: Graphic Materials
  - Photographs of native peoples of Washington State, taken in conjunction with the fieldwork of Willard Rhodes. By Juel E. Lange (NW Coast), 17 black-and-white photographic prints, 8 x 10 in. (Box-folder 2/15)
    Selected photos were used in the published booklet accompanying the original edition of Music of the American Indian: Northwest (Puget Sound) AFS L34, recorded and edited by Willard Rhodes.
  - Photos – Sioux, schoolchildren, Pueblos, Navajo and BIA school photos from Bureau of Indian Affairs., 1 color, 22 black-and-white photographic prints (various sizes); 11 negatives (Box-folder 2/16)